Guide to the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection
1657-1975
12/1969-081
University of Houston. Libraries. Special Collections Department
4.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection consists of manuscripts from a variety of sources. Included are correspondence, legal documents, printed documents, and other formats. In addition to original documents, some folders also contain transcriptions, translations, or preliminary research notes.
Historical Note:
Special Collections collects and preserves historically significant materials. Its holdings comprise a rare book collection and ten main archival collecting areas. In some instances, Special Collections gathers materials on a single topic to preserve them and make them available. In these cases, Special Collections is seen as the creator of the artificially constructed collection.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre)
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Related Materials:
Early Texas Documents collection (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcardandid=465)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of manuscripts from a variety of sources. Included are correspondence, legal documents, printed documents, and other formats. In addition to original documents, some folders also contain transcriptions, translations, or preliminary research notes.
Where possible, documents clustered around particular themes or collecting areas have been grouped into series. Within the first four series, items are arranged alphabetically by author or signatory name when possible, otherwise alphabetically by title or description.
Further accessions to the collection have been assigned their own accession numbers and are described in the fifth series. These materials are arranged according to date of acquisition.
Detailed List of Contents
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts arranged alphabetically
  - Alabama legal documents, 1819, 1836, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Atkinson, Judge Norman, Harris County. Autograph letter signed, letterhead, March 17, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Gift of Frell Albright
  - Bagby, Arthur P., Tuscaloosa, Alabama, July 24, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benard, G. Autograph document signed, February 14, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gift of Mrs. Marian B. Enslow, October 1975
  - Bishop, Sir Henry Rowley (composer). Autograph letter signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bosanquet, Eustace F. (member of the Bibliographical Society). Autograph letter signed to Sir George Fordham, October 23, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bradley, Roland. Typed signed letters to Bradley (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bradley, Roland. Regarding “The Three-Quarter Century Mark Celebration and Exposition” and the proposed Texas Polytechnical Institute, approximately 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “The Three-Quarter Century Mark Celebration and Exposition” and the proposed Texas Polytechnical Institute, approximately 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brewer, Marcel. Printed document signed. To Howard Barnstone, October 12, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift of Howard Barnstone
  - Checks and ledgers, 1800s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cincotta, Hector Dante. Oda Italiana, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Connally, Tom. Typed letter signed. To Dr. G.V. Brindley, April 28, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Gift of Mrs. G.V. Brindley, October 1970
  - Dobie, James Frank. Autograph letter signed to Alfred Vincent Kidder, September 13, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Duniway, Abigail Scott. Photograph, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Education in the South, probably 1866 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - “Excellency” autograph letter signed regarding a publication “devoted to the calamities of Louis XVI… [and] the virtues of the King of Great Britain,” London, February 22, 1807 or 1809 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Field, Cyrus, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Georgia land document, March 25, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hall files (Box 1, Folder 20)
    from the Judge James Hall estate
  - Hawke, Rohn. Correspondence regarding original script of Shakespeare programs, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Gift of Pruett, February 2, 1969
  - Hawke, Rohn. Original Script of Shakespeare programs and press clippings. Waco, TX, approximately 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Howe, Julia Ward. Autograph letter signed, October 15, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Johnson, Philip. Two autograph letters signed to Howard Barnstone, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jovanovich, William (President of Harcourt, Brace and World) to Robert D. Franklin (Director of the Toledo Public Library), June 27, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - “The Life and Times of a Wayward Person.” Tagalong, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lind, Jenny plates (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Livingston, Edward. Autograph letter signed., undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Louisiana legal, property, and financial documents, 1853, 1834, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Mazzone, Giovanni, Emancipation document attested to by Domenico Martinetti, Notary Ducal of Turin, September 23, 1657 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Gift of Frell Albright, December 1976
  - McKenzie, J.A. Autograph letter signed, 3pp. account of a trip to New Orleans, approximately 1850 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Gift of Frell Albright, Decmeber 1976
  - Mendelsohn, Erich. Autograph letter signed, to Dr. Grunbaum, June 25, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miller, Jaoquin. Autograph letter signed, 1p., to Mrs. Gladstone, May 21, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Monod, Adophe. Saint Paul. w/handwritten translation, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Gift of Mrs. Elmer J. Rodenberg From the Judge James Hall estate
  - New Mexico water rights document, 1880s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold. Autograph (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Gift of Lorene Pouncey
  - Pariset, Francois-Georges. Letter, Bordeaux, France, February 15, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Radspinner, William Ambrose. Calendar, 1976, with attachments (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Gift of “None Other than William Ambrose Radspinner”, January 1977
  - Randolph, Beverly, (8th Governor of Virginia). Autograph letter signed, Richmond, December 19, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Rainer, S.M., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Henry David, December 1969
  - Ransom, Harry. Autograph letter, to Mr. Candler, November 29, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Schuyler, Peter (New Jersey), May 21, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sermons (2), delivered at Norwald and Rye, 1790, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Hall estate
  - Sparks, Jared. Autograph letter signed. Accepts an invitation and mentions his wife is in America, August 18 [no year] (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Starr, Lydia. Teaching contract with Orchard Hill School (Georgia). Found in Junior High Speller, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Staub, John. Sketch of Mrs. H.R. Cullen's bath (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Tennessee legal documents, 1795, 1809, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - U.S. Government printed documents (Washington, D.C.), 1853, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Wilson, James P. Questions on the Bible (Box 1, Folder 52)
    From the Judge James Hall estate
  - Wortham, Lyndall (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Mailgram from Lady Bird Johnson (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 1)
    - Letter from the University of Texas regarding the class of 1912 (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 2)
    - Packet with photographs, newspaper articles, postcards from Egypt, bookmark, page from Departure and Havana, Galveston Historical Foundation life member card (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 3)
    - Handwritten speeches (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 4)
    - List of people and addresses (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 5)
    - Letter from Houston Museum of Fine Arts (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 6)
    - Handwritten notes about "around the world on a frayed shoestring" (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 7)
  - Letter to Archibald Yell (second governor of Arkansas), July 20, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Description of the Convention-Parliament offering the Crown to the Prince and Princess of Orange, which completed the Glorious Revolution, 1688.", undated (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 1)
  - Devonshire. Last Will and Testament, written at Devonshire, 1704 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 2)
    Gift of Mr. Boyd Armstrong, May 1975
  - District of Norfolk and Portsmouth merchandise document, April 13 1805 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 3)
  - Kite Instructions. Young America Kite Company. Broadside Folio. Contains both instructions and patterns, 1869 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 4)
    Gift of Mr. Frell Albright
  - Louisiana Plantation Payroll, 1866 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 5)
  - Napolean I, Emperor of the French declaration/broadside, July 29, 1802 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 6)
    Gift of Harold G. Richardson
  - “To George the Second King of Great Britain [etc.] The Humble Address of the People called Quakers”, approximately 1727 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 7)
  - “To the Public” resolution regarding the United States Bank, Samuel Quimby, Anti-Jackson meeting, and Henry Clay. C.K Sinner, Chairman, L.W. Hall and A.G. Holmes Secretaries, undated (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 8)
  - Western District, Orleans Territory. Land document, July 12, 1811 (Ovs box 2, Ovs folder 9)
- U.S. Presidents and National Political Figures
  - Johnson, Lady Bird and Lyndon B. Typed signed letters to Lyndall Wortham, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wortham, Lyndall (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Mailgram from Ladybird Johnson (Box 1, Folder 53, Item 1)
  - Burr, Aaron, autograph manuscript unsigned, 1802 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Douglas, Stephen A., signature, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Forsythe, John, autograph letter signed, 1837, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hamilton, Alexander, receipt for Treasury Department, June 3, 1793 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jackson, Andrew, partly printed document signed, State of Tennessee, March 18, 1805 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Gift of William B. Bates
  - Kennedy, John, typed letter signed to Mrs. Ann Napoletan, Houston, July 10, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, autographed note signed, introducting Col. R.W. Thompson, June 11, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Nourse, Joseph, to Aaron Burr, August 25, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tyler, John, 1841, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Webster, Daniel, printed resolution, May 26, 1836 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Webster, Daniel, signature, approximately 1845-1850 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Van Buren, Martin, D.S. Naval Appointment of C.R.P. Rogers, July 8, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Adams, John Quincy, document signed, passport for Doctor Joseph Cloud Junior, Washington, October 2, 1823 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 1)
  - Buchanan, James, printed document signed, passport for Warren Prince, Washington DC, February 14, 1849 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 2)
  - Buchanan, James, secretarial proxy signature on party printed General Land Office document, acknowledging full payment for 40 acres by John Hall of Polk County Missouri, June 1, 1859 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 3)
  - Fillmore, Millard. Signed Land Office Land Office Certificate for grant of land in Missouri to James W. Nolin, November 1, 1852 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 4)
  - Forsythe, John, partly printed document signed, passport for Dr. Ferdinand Stewart and family, August 14, 1840 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 5)
  - Madison, James, document signed, appointing Caleb Hopkins of New York Collector for the District of Gennesee, Washington, June 21, 1809 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 6)
  - Jackson, Andrew, letters patent signed, Washington, May 13, 1834 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 7)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, document signed, appointing William Commons Assistant Surgeon in the Navy, February 26, 1864 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 8)
    Gift of Dr. John O. King
  - Pinckney, Charles, printed document signed, South Caroline land grant with survey attached. Land granted to Jacob Boughman, 500 acres. Columbia, South Carolina, March 6, 1797 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 9)
  - Van Buren, Martin, document signed, General Land Office document for Etheldred Owens of Montomery County, Alabama, August 1, 1838 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 10)
- Civil War-era Documents
  - Union
    - U.S. Department of War, Annual book of general orders for officers in the US Army, 1863-1864 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Included in margins are hand written notes by the officer who owned the book.
    - Printed discharge of liability from military duty, September 12, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Printed orders, Missouri, February, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Post war ordnance return, October 9, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Folio cabinet photo showing Sumner with nine members of his staff. Sumner, Major General. E.V. Warrenton, 13 November 1862 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Gift of Mr. Frell Albright, December 1976
  - Confederate
    - “A piece of hat worn by Ex-President Davis while in Atlanta Georgia.” Annie M. Barns, autographed letter signed, to Wm. F. Gable, Duluth, GA, November 13, 1886, November 30, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Benjamin, Judah, P., letter signed, Richmond, March 7, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Brumbelow, William, autograph Letter signed, written from Chattanooga, Tennessee to his wife. Describes war activity and family matters., August 10, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Confederate Resolution, “An Act to Authorize the President to Enlist Troops for Special Service,” Richmond, approximately 1860-1862 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Gift of George Britton, November 1976
    - Confederate States of America, Congress, Excerpts from the record, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Jackson, T.J. “Stonewall”, autograph letter signed to Robert E. Lee, on the day before his mortal wounding, May 1, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Lee, Robert E. autograph letter signed, to Brig. Gen. Ed. Johnson, April 18, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Louisiana tax assessments for Bacon and Agricultural Products, 1864, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Nash, James H. autograph letter signed, Richmond, October 9, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - “Original War Songs for Southern Soldiers and their Loved Ones at Home,” printed song sheet, approximately 1863-1865 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Setley, Henry Albert. “A Few Rhymes On The Naval Expedition To Port Royal” and “The Battle Of Drainesville”, Camp Pierpoint, December, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 78th Regiment, O.V.U.S.A., printed documents (2), October 22, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - U.S. Supreme Court document appointing Alexander Stephens as an Attorney and Counsellor, January 6, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Willis, Edward, letter to Maj. W.H. Taylor (with subsequent notes in a different hand), March 23, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Slave Documents
  Documents in this series are arranged by state or territory.
  - Etat de la Louisiane. Paroisse St. Landry. Bureau des Hypotheques. (Louisiana, St. Landry Parish), January 9, 1840 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    In French
  - Sutton, Daniel, document signed. Opeloussas, St. Landry Parish, Louisiana., October 12, 1811 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Maryland. Charles County, March 8, 1830 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mississippi Territory. Baldwin County, Washington District (3 items), 1810, July 16, 1810, June 12, 1814 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mississippi Territory. Washington District, Baldwin County (3 items), July 28, 1809, August 1809, February 3, 1812 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Louisiana. St. Landry Parish, June 14, 1841 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 11)
  - State of Louisiana. Bill of Purchase for one male slave, January 15, 1859 (Ovs box 5, Ovs folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts arranged by date of acquisition
  - Standard Oil Co., S.A. Argentina. Photo Postcards, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Accession #2016-022
  - Keeland, J.W. Deeds, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Accession #2016-023
  - Gilbert and Barker Manufacturing Co. "Organizational History", 1955-1965 [1884] (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Accession #2016-024
  - Mamie Baack Abstract of title, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Accession #2016-035